Finding Aid for Black Action Movement I, II and III select documents
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Black Action Movement I, II and III select documents 1970-1987
Bentley Historical Library.
55.6 MB online
2014162 Aa 3
Digitized select documents relating to the Black Action Movement (BAM) I, II, and III on the University of Michigan campus, 1970-1987.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Digitized from holdings of the Bentley Historical Library in 2014
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Black Action Movement (BAM) was formed in 1970 from a coalition of the Black Student Union, the Black Law Students Association, the Association of Black Social Work Students, and groups of black students from the Medical School and the Psychology Department. BAM initiated a series of protests by the University of Michigan African American students against the policies and actions of the university administration, that took place in 1970 (BAM I), 1975 (BAM II), and 1987 (BAM III).
The BAM I campaign was one of the most successful in campus history. Over three hundred professors and teaching assistants cancelled classes and many departments were shut down. After eight days, the university gave approval to the essential demands of increased minority aid, services, and staff, and agreed to work toward a goal of 10% African-American enrollment by 1973. The BAM II campaign of 1975 aimed its protests against the lack of progress by the University in fulfilling negotiations of BAM I, expulsion of Black nursing student, and University's rejection of Regent approved Black candidate for L,S,&A deanship. The BAM III of 1987 protest began as a result of issues related to admissions and faculty, racist remarks of the student WJJX radio disc jockey, University Housing's efforts to address harassment of Black students in Residence Halls, and University and Ann Arbor Police Department's handling of fight at South Quad. In 1987 the University established the Michigan Mandate under President James Duderstadt. Its goal was to increase representation of Students of Color at the University of Michigan.
The following selection of documents, mostly from the records of the Office of the President with some articles from The Michigan Daily and the University Record, is intended to provide an overview of the Black Action Movement (BAM) demands and the university's immediate response in each of the three phases of the Black Action Movement. It represents a small portion of the documentation of BAM contained in the records of various university units, personal papers, photograph collections, and publications held by the Bentley Historical Library. All the records are open to researchers, subject to some limited restrictions (student records protected by FERPA; personnel records, and certain administrative records subject to review).
Subjects:
African-American college students--Political activity--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African-American law students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Student movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Genre Terms:
Digital images.
- BAM I
  - The demands
    - "The Black Action Movement," 1970
      (Box 107, President (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 2 pages)
    - The United Black Population of the University of Michigan, "Black Student Demands," undated
      (Box 106, President (University of Michigan) Records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 6 pages)
  - The response
    - R.W. Fleming to the Members of the Black Action Movement, with attachment "Administration Proposes 7-Point Plan for Minority Admissions," March 5, 1970
      (Box 107, President (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 3 pages)
    - "To the Members of the Black Action Movement," undated
      (Box 107, President (University of Michigan) Records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 3 pages)
    - "Statement by Vice-President Stephen H. Spurr," March 18, 1970
      (Box 107, President (University of Michigan) Records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 2 pages)
    - Arthur M. Ross to faculty and staff, "Response of Regents to BAM Demands," March 20, 1970
    - R.W. Fleming, "Statement" March 27, 1970
    - "University response to original 12 Black Action Movement Demands," March 29, 1970
    - Board of Regents University of Michigan, "Statement" April 1, 1970
      (Box 106, President (University of Michigan) Records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 2pages)
    - Black Action Movement, "Press Statement," April 2, 1970
    - R.W. Fleming, "Announcement" April 3, 1970
      (Box 106, President (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 3 pages)
- BAM II
  - The demands
    - "'75 BAM demands"
      (Michigan Daily, February 19, 1975 page 8)
    - "Minorities Still Hold Ad. Bldg"
      (Michigan Daily, February 20, 1975 page 8)
    - Rob Meachum, "Ad. Bldg. sit-in: Talks on demands to continue Monday"
      (Michigan Daily, February 21, 1975 pages 1, 2)
    - "Demands of the Black Action Movement," February 18, 1975
      (Box 109, President (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 4 pages)
    - Black Faculty and Staff Association of the University of Michigan, "Media Statement" February 19, 1975
      (Box 109, President (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 2 pages)
  - The response
    - R.W. Fleming offer to the students who have occupied the 2nd floor of the Administration Building February 20, 1974 (sic) and undated
    - R.W. Fleming to the students who have occupied the 2nd floor of the Administration Building February 20, 1974 (sic.)
      (Box 109, President (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 1 page)
    - University of Michigan News and Information Services, Press Release February 20, 1975
- BAM III
  - The demands
    - "B.A.M. III Black Action Movement. 3/18 copy to Executive Officers DEstep, VNordby"
      (Box 22, Vice President for Student Affairs (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 3 pages)
  - The response
    - " University announces six-point action plan to increase representation of Blacks"
      (University Record, Special Edition, March 25, 1987 Volume 42, Number 26, 4 pages)
    - James J. Duderstadt, "Regents' Communication. Action Item. Creation of the Position of Vice Provost for Minority Affairs" April 1987
      (Box 225, Vice President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 1 page)
    - James J. Duderstadt to colleagues involved with BAM negotiations April 28, 1987
      (2 pages) enclosing advance copy of 6-Point Plan Report (17 pages), Box 225, Vice President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.)
    - Advance copy of 6-Point Plan Report
      (17pages), Box 225, Vice President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan. (Enclosed with James J. Duderstadt to colleagues involved with BAM negotiations, April 28, 1987)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library holds a number of archival collections related to the Black Action Movement:
President. Records, 1967-, Boxes 106-109. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87274]
Center for Afroamerican Studies. Records, 1966-2010, Boxes 1 & 2. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-2012140]
Office of Budgets and Planning. Records, 1970-1979. Box 5. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87295]
Vice-President for Development. Records, 1948-1984. Box 8, 9. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87366]
Residential College Student/Faculty Research Community. Reports, 1978-, 0. 1 foot. (Report on BAM strike).
School of Education. Records, 1904-, Box 2. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87114]
John L. Erlich (Collector). Printed Materials, 1966-1970. 1 foot. (News clippings).
Madison James Foster. Papers, 1969-1977. 1 foot. (BAM participant). [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-85165]
Bret Eynon (Collector). Papers, 1966-1977. 1 foot. (Oral interviews with participants). [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-85166]
Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs. Records, 1947-, Boxes 28, 175-181. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87365-1]
College of Engineering. Records, 1873-, 18 feet. Boxes 15, 16. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-8781]
Vice-President for Student Affairs. Records, 1908-, 18 feet. Box 9. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87290]
To expand this topic to include a broader look at minority affairs at the university, other sources are relevant:
Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs. Files of Niara Sudarkasa, boxes 258-260; files of Robert Holmes, Boxes 255, 256.
Vice-President for Student Affairs, Boxes 10-17. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87290]
Ross School of Business. Records, 1916-, Boxes 41, 42. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87296]
Housing Office. Records, 1923-, Boxes 1, 2, 5, 7. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-87296]